Guide to the Helen and Newton Harrison Papers M1797
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
- Series 2. Project Files, 1969-2011
  - Subseries 34. Tibet is the High Ground, 1990-1991, 2005-2008
    This subseries consists of budgets, correspondence, project descriptions, exhibition information, photographic material, planning, notes, press, research, and text, as well as material about the Committee for Friends of the Tibetan High Ground. At the request of the Dalai Lama, the project began in the early 1990s with a conceptual design for the former forested lands of the Tibetan Plateau. The Harrisons explored the potential of putting together a team of experts to create an “analog forest” to run parallel to the Dalai Lama’s vision of a World Peace Park. The Harrisons were introduced to this project through colleague Robert (Bob) Livingston, the Dalai Lama’s science advisor and Professor of Neurosciences Emeritus, University of California, San Diego. The subseries also contains material about The Missing Peace: The Dalai Lama Portrait Project traveling exhibition (2005 to 2009). The subseries is arranged alphabetically.
    See also: Series 2. Project Files, Subseries 72. Force Majeure
    - Tibet; Budget, 1990 (Box 68, Folder 16)
    - Tibet; Committee for Friends of the Tibetan High Ground, 1991 (Box 68, Folder 17)
    - Tibet; Correspondence, 1990-1991 (Box 68, Folder 18)
    - Tibet; Dalai Lama Ad Hoc Science Advisory Group Meeting UCSD Faculty Club 9 March 1992 (Box 68, Folder 19)
    - Tibet; Descriptions, 1991, undated (Box 68, Folder 20)
    - Tibet; Exhibitions, Art on the Map, Chicago Cultural Center, 1994 (Box 68, Folder 21)
    - Tibet; Exhibitions, "The Missing Peace: Artists Consider the Dalai Lama" traveling exhibition, Correspondence, 2005-2008 (Box 68, Folder 22)
    - Tibet; Exhibitions, "The Missing Peace: Artists Consider the Dalai Lama" traveling exhibition, Publicity, 2006-2008 (Box 68, Folder 23)
    - Tibet; Lannan Foundation Visual Arts Grant Application and the University of Colorado at Boulder, undated (Box 68, Folder 24)
    - Tibet; Photographic material, Photographs, undated (Box 68, Folder 25)
    - Tibet; Photographic material, Photographs, undated (Box 69, Folder 1)
      Notes
      Copies
    - Tibet; Photographic material, Slides, undated (Box 69, Folder 2)
    - Tibet; Planning and notes, 1991, undated (Box 69, Folder 3)
    - Tibet; Press, 1991, 2006 (Box 69, Folder 4)
    - Tibet; Research, 1987, 1990-1992 (Box 69, Folder 5)
    - Tibet; Text, 1991, undated (Box 69, Folder 6)
    - Tibet; Tibet is the High Ground packets, 1990-1991 (Box 69, Folder 7)
  - Subseries 35. Cergy-Pontoise, 1991-1993
    This subseries consists of contact information, correspondence, project descriptions, maps, planning, notes, presentation information, research, and text documenting the Harrisons’ work in Cergy-Pontoise, France. Invited by the Minister of Culture in charge of the Ring Cities of Paris, the Planning Department of the City of Cergy-Pontoise, and the School of Architecture at Cergy-Pontoise’s summer program, the work examined an area that had developed too fast. The area had previously been made up of small farms and communities. The Harrisons proposed a promenade to connect people to the Oise River. This project is also referred to “A Promenade ‘Ecologique’ for Cergy-Pontoise.” The subseries is arranged alphabetically.
    - Cergy-Pontoise; A la Recontre de L'axe Majeur et de L'axe Historique Parisien conference, Les Ateliers d'Ete de Cergy, 1994 (Flat-box 270, Folder 1)
    - Cergy-Pontoise; Contact information, undated (Box 69, Folder 8)
    - Cergy-Pontoise; Correspondence [RESTRICTED], 1991-1992 (Box 260, Folder 9)
    - Cergy-Pontoise; Correspondence, 1991-1993 (Box 69, Folder 9)
    - Cergy-Pontoise; Correspondence, undated (Box 69, Folder 10)
    - Cergy-Pontoise; Invoices [RESTRICTED], 1992 (Box 260, Folder 10)
    - Cergy-Pontoise; Maps, undated (Box 69, Folder 11)
    - Cergy-Pontoise; Maps, undated (Map-folder 332)
    - Cergy-Pontoise; Maps, undated (Map-folder 436)
    - Cergy-Pontoise; Planning and notes, undated (Box 69, Folder 12)
    - Cergy-Pontoise; Presentations, Les Ateliers d'Ete de Cergy, Abbaye de Royaumont, Asnières sur Oise, France, 1991 (Box 69, Folder 13)
    - Cergy-Pontoise; Presentations, Les Ateliers d'Ete de Cergy, Abbaye de Royaumont, Asnières-Oise, France, 1991 (Flat-box 269, Folder 15)
    - Cergy-Pontoise; Presentations, Note de Presentation de L'exposition pour Differents Partenaires "La Riviere-Riviere" Cergy-Pontoise Ville au Bord de L'eau, 1992 (Box 70, Folder 1)
    - Cergy-Pontoise; Research, 1987, 1991-1992, undated (Box 70, Folder 2)
    - Cergy-Pontoise; Text, 1987, 1991-1992, undated (Box 70, Folder 3)
  - Subseries 36. Elbe, 1991-1995
    This subseries consists of correspondence, planning, notes, maps, photographic material, research, and text. For this project, the Harrisons proposed to reclaim the Elbe watershed (sometimes referred to as the Labe Watershed), which stretches from the mountains of Bohemia through Germany to the outfall of the Elbe in the North Sea. The Harrisons were first invited by Milan Knizak at the Prague Academy of Art in 1990. The Harrisons researched and worked on this project while working at the Bauhaus Dessau. It is part of a larger concept for reclaiming pit mines in Bitterfeld, Germany; Northern Bohemia; and Czechoslovakia. The subseries is arranged alphabetically.
    See also Series 2. Project Files, Subseries 38. Bauhaus Dessau; Series 2. Project Files, Subseries 41, ArQule; Series 2. Project Files, Subseries 42, Silver Lake
    - Elbe; Correspondence, 1990-1993, 1995 (Box 70, Folder 4)
    - Elbe; Czechoslovakia information from Ivana Rothbauerová, 1991 (Box 70, Folder 5)
    - Elbe; Planning and notes, 1993, undated (Box 70, Folder 6)
    - Elbe; Map, 1991 (Box 70, Folder 7)
      from Ivana Rothbauerová
    - Elbe; Map, 1991 (Map-folder 333)
    - Elbe; Maps, 1981, 1985, 1988-1990 (Map-folder 334)
    - Elbe; Maps, undated (Box 70, Folder 8)
    - Elbe; Photographic material, undated (Box 70, Folder 9)
    - Elbe; Research, 1990-1991 (Flat-box 275, Folder 1)
    - Elbe; Research, 1990-1994, undated (Box 70, Folder 10)
    - Elbe; Research, undated (Box 70, Folder 11)
    - Elbe; Text, undated (Box 70, Folder 12)
  - Subseries 37. San Diego Landfill, 1991-1992
    This subseries consists of contact information, contracts and agreements, correspondence, project descriptions, maps, meeting information, planning, notes, schedules, research, and text. In 1991, the architectural firm of Martinez, Cutri, and McArdle invited the Harrisons to join them as artists and conceptual designers for a competition to create the master plan for the San Diego Landfill. The Harrisons created a vision statement for the proposal. Their group, a team of architects, landscape architects, engineers, graphic designers, and another artist, won the competition. The plan was approved by the City of San Diego. Another name for this project is Miramar Landfill. The subseries is arranged alphabetically.
    - San Diego Landfill; Contact information, 1991 (Box 71, Folder 1)
    - San Diego Landfill; Contracts and agreements, 1991 (Box 71, Folder 2)
    - San Diego Landfill; Correspondence, 1991-1992, 1994 (Box 71, Folder 3)
    - San Diego Landfill; Descriptions, 1991-1992 (Box 71, Folder 4)
    - San Diego Landfill; Maps, 1991 (Box 71, Folder 5)
    - San Diego Landfill; Maps, 1991 (Flat-box 275, Folder 2)
    - San Diego Landfill; Martinez, Cutri and McArdle, 1991 (Box 71, Folder 6)
      SF 254 form
    - San Diego Landfill; Meetings, 1991 (Box 71, Folder 7)
    - San Diego Landfill; Miramar Landfill Facility Development Plan, 1991 (Box 71, Folder 8)
    - San Diego Landfill; Our Landfill: A Restoration, General Development Plan, Preliminary Draft, 1992 (Box 71, Folder 9)
    - San Diego Landfill; Planning and notes, 1991-1992 (Box 71, Folder 10)
    - San Diego Landfill; Project schedule, 1991 (Box 71, Folder 11)
    - San Diego Landfill; Text, 1991 (Box 71, Folder 12)
  - Subseries 38. Bauhaus Dessau, 1992-1995
    This subseries consists of contracts and agreements, general information, schedule and programming information about the Bauhaus Dessau, correspondence, project descriptions, photographic material, planning, notes, research, and text. Prior to their work on the Mulde River and Bitterfeld, Germany, the Harrisons worked on a project for the Elbe watershed in Bohemia and Czechoslovakia, which is directly linked to their work at the Bauhaus Dessau.
    The proposal, “Ruminations on the Open Pit Mines at Bitterfeld” (1992), was created by the Harrisons at a Bauhaus Dessau workshop coordinated by the Chamber of Architects of Hessen. The workshop asked the attendees what to do with the 24 square kilometer brown coal excavations at Bitterfeld. Attendees included Ennert Wehberg (landscape architect), Carlo Weber (architect), Lalo Nicolic (architect and President of the Chamber), Rolf Toyka (Director of Advanced Education in Architecture for the Chamber of Architects at Hessen), other architects, and students. Proceedings of the symposium, published by Prestel Press, Bitterfeld: Braunkohlebrachen – Probleme, Chancen, Visionen, won one of two 2nd place prizes (no first place prizes were given out) from the Ministry of the Ecology of Sachsen-Anhart and several Art/Natur Organizations.
    The Bitterfeld work became the basis for the Harrisons’ Mulde proposal: “The Muldeaue: The First Design for an Eco-Urban Edge for the Mulde River from the Muldestausee to the Elbe” (1993). In this work, the Harrisons, proposed a redesign between the urban and natural forms of the Muldeaue.
    Both of these projects, done around the same time at the Bauhaus Dessau, are part of a larger concept for reclaiming pit mines in Bitterfeld, Germany; Northern Bohemia; and Czechoslovakia.
    See also Series 2. Project Files, Subseries 36. Elbe; Series 2. Project Files, Subseries 41, ArQule; Series 2. Project Files, Subseries 42, Silver Lake
    - Bauhaus; Bauhaus Declarations on Water Sustainability, undated (Box 71, Folder 13)
    - Bauhaus; Bitterfeld Die Erde heilen, 1996 (Box 71, Folder 14)
      by Deutsches Museum für Garten, Landschaft und Ökologie
    - Bauhaus; Bitterfeld, Descriptions, undated (Box 71, Folder 15)
    - Bauhaus; Bitterfeld, Photographic material, 1992 (Box 71, Folder 16)
    - Bauhaus; Bitterfeld, Research, 1991 (Flat-box 275, Folder 3)
    - Bauhaus; Bitterfeld, Text, 1992 (Box 71, Folder 17)
    - Bauhaus; Contracts and agreements, 1993 (Box 71, Folder 18)
    - Bauhaus; Correspondence, 1992-1995 (Box 72, Folder 1)
    - Bauhaus; Grübeleien: Über die Stillegung des Braunkohletagebaus bei Bitterfeld und den Zustand des Wassers, der Erde und der luft, 1992 (Box 72, Folder 2)
    - Bauhaus; Mulde, Das Muldeauen - Einzugsgebiet exhibition, Münchner Volkshochschule am Gasteig, München, Germany, 1995 (Box 72, Folder 3)
    - Bauhaus; Mulde, Descriptions, 1992-1994 (Box 72, Folder 4)
    - Bauhaus; Mulde, Photographic material, undated (Box 72, Folder 5)
    - Bauhaus; Mulde, Text, English, 1992-1995 (Box 72, Folder 6)
    - Bauhaus; Mulde, Text, German, 1992-1995 (Box 72, Folder 7)
    - Bauhaus; Planning and notes, 1992-1995 (Box 72, Folder 8)
    - Bauhaus; Programming, Classes and workshops, Bauhaus Dessau, Germany, 1993 (Box 72, Folder 9)
    - Bauhaus; Programming, Colloquiums, Bauhaus Dessau, Germany, 1994 (Box 72, Folder 10)
    - Bauhaus; Programming, Water Forums, Bauhaus Dessau, Germany, 1993-1995 (Box 72, Folder 11)
    - Bauhaus; Research, 1991, 1994-1995 (Box 72, Folder 12)
    - Bauhaus; Schedule, 1991 (Flat-box 275, Folder 4)
  - Subseries 39. Hawaii, 1992-1995
    This subseries consists of contact information, correspondence, planning, notes, and research. The Harrisons started work on this project for Kau, one of Hawaii’s last rural agricultural districts. The community wanted to stay rural and develop as an environmental and cultural model for the state. The subseries is arranged chronologically.
    - Hawaii, 1992-1995 (Box 72, Folder 13)
  - Subseries 40. Serpentine Lattice, 1992-1994
    This subseries consists of catalogs, contact information, correspondence, project descriptions, exhibition information, maps, meeting information, posters, photographic material, press, research, schedules, and text for this project. Commissioned by the Douglas F. Cooley Memorial Art Gallery at Reed College in Portland, Oregon, this multimedia installation examined the past and potential future for the North American Pacific Coast temperate rainforest. It presented a plan to reclaim and preserve the forests in the Pacific Northwest. It used slides, maps, text, and sketches to visually lay out the entire 1,800 miles of the forest ecosystem from Northern California to Southern Alaska. The subseries is arranged alphabetically.
    - Serpentine Lattice; Acknowledgements, undated (Box 73, Folder 1)
    - Serpentine Lattice; Catalog, 1993 (Box 73, Folder 2)
    - Serpentine Lattice; Contact information, undated (Box 73, Folder 3)
    - Serpentine Lattice; Correspondence, 1992-1994 (Box 73, Folder 4)
    - Serpentine Lattice; Descriptions, 1993-1994 (Box 73, Folder 5)
    - Serpentine Lattice; Exhibitions, Comments from unidentified exhibition, undated (Box 73, Folder 6)
    - Serpentine Lattice; Exhibitions, Douglas F. Cooley Memorial Art Gallery, Reed College, Portland, OR, 1993 (Box 73, Folder 7)
    - Serpentine Lattice; Exhibitions, Exhibition Tour Schedule, 1993-1994 (Box 73, Folder 8)
    - Serpentine Lattice; Exhibitions, Hatton Gallery, Colorado State University, Fort Collins, CO, 2000 (Box 73, Folder 9)
    - Serpentine Lattice; Exhibitions, Ronald Feldman Fine Arts, New York City, NY, 1993 (Box 73, Folder 10)
    - Serpentine Lattice; Exhibitions, Maps, 1991, 1993, undated (Box 73, Folder 11)
    - Serpentine Lattice; Exhibitions, Meetings and conversations, 1993 (Box 73, Folder 12)
    - Serpentine Lattice; Maps, 1987, 1990, 1993 (Map-folder 335)
    - Serpentine Lattice; Maps and posters, 1990, 1993, 2000, undated (Map-folder 437)
    - Serpentine Lattice; Photographic material, Negatives, undated (Box 73, Folder 13)
    - Serpentine Lattice; Photographic material, Photographs (Photocopies), 1989 (Flat-box 270, Folder 2)
    - Serpentine Lattice; Photographic material, Photographs, undated (Box 73, Folder 14)
    - Serpentine Lattice; Press, 1992-1994 (Box 73, Folder 15)
    - Serpentine Lattice; Research, Agriculture and soil, 1988-1989, undated (Box 73, Folder 16)
    - Serpentine Lattice; Research, Arts and entertainment, 1992-1993 (Box 74, Folder 1)
    - Serpentine Lattice; Research, Arts and entertainment, 1993 (Flat-box 270)
    - Serpentine Lattice; Research, Bibliographies, undated (Box 74, Folder 2)
    - Serpentine Lattice; Research, Conservation and environment, 1981, 1983-1987, 1989 (Box 74, Folder 3)
    - Serpentine Lattice; Research, Conservation and environment, 1991 (Box 74, Folder 4)
    - Serpentine Lattice; Research, Conservation and environment, 1992 (Box 74, Folder 5)
    - Serpentine Lattice; Research, Conservation and environment, undated (Box 75, Folder 1)
    - Serpentine Lattice; Research, Deadwood, OR, 1991, 1993, undated (Box 75, Folder 2)
    - Serpentine Lattice; Research, Forests, 1969, 1979, 1983-1984, 1990-1993 (Box 75, Folder 3)
    - Serpentine Lattice; Research, Forests, undated (Box 75, Folder 4)
    - Serpentine Lattice; Research, Forests, The Ancient Forests of the Pacific Northwest: Protecting a Vanishing Ecosystem (Ed. Heather Diefenderfer), 1992 (Box 75, Folders 5-6, Box 76, Folders 1-3)
    - Serpentine Lattice; Research, Forests, The Ancient Forests of the Pacific Northwest: Protecting a Vanishing Ecosystem (Ed. Heather Diefenderfer) - Cover, 1992 (Flat-box 270, Folder 3)
    - Serpentine Lattice; Research, Pacific Northwest, 1988, 1991, 1994, undated (Box 76, Folder 4)
    - Serpentine Lattice; Research, Salmon, 1992, undated (Box 76, Folder 5)
    - Serpentine Lattice; Research, School of Agriculture and Allied Arts at the University of Oregon, 1992-1993 (Box 76, Folder 6)
    - Serpentine Lattice; Research, Skokomish Indian Tribe, 1992-1993 (Box 76, Folder 7)
    - Serpentine Lattice; Research, Trinity County, CA, 1993 (Box 76, Folder 8)
    - Serpentine Lattice; Schedule and trip notes, 1993 (Box 76, Folder 9)
    - Serpentine Lattice; Text, English, 1993, undated (Box 76, Folder 10)
    - Serpentine Lattice; Text, German, undated (Box 76, Folder 11)
    - Serpentine Lattice; Text; Three sheets all the same text panel, 1992 (Map-tube MT #5)
      Looks like the three sheets were used to make each other.
  - Subseries 41. ArQule, 1993-1994
    This subseries consists of contact information, contracts and agreements, correspondence, and meeting information. The material in this subseries documents the partnership between ArQule, a company run by synthetic organic chemist Joseph Hogan; Sevin Rosen; and the Harrison Studio to use Hogan’s technology to clean contaminated water. For this project, which never left the planning stages, the Harrisons would provide visionary plans and concepts using their “whole systems” approach to environmental problems. The subseries is arranged alphabetically.
    See also Series 2. Project Files, Subseries 38. Bauhaus; Series 2. Project Files, Subseries 42. Silver Lake
    - ArQule; Contracts and agreements, 1994 (Box 77, Folder 1)
    - ArQule; Correspondence, 1993-1994 (Box 77, Folder 2)
    - ArQule; Minutes and conversations, 1993-1994 (Box 77, Folder 3)
    - ArQule; Planning and notes, 1993-1994 (Box 77, Folder 4)
    - ArQule; Project Players, 1993-1994 (Box 77, Folder 5)
  - Subseries 42. Silver Lake, 1993-1994
    This subseries consists of contact information, correspondence, meeting information, planning, notes, and research. The material in this subseries documents the partnership between ArQule, a company run by synthetic organic chemist Joseph Hogan; Sevin Rosen; and the Harrison Studio to use Hogan’s technology to cleanup Silver Lake, an extremely polluted lake near Bitterfeld, Germany. For this project, which never left the planning stages, the Harrisons, using their “whole systems” approach, wanted to integrate Hogan’s technology into the clean up of Silver Lake. The subseries is arranged alphabetically.
    See also Series 2. Project Files, Subseries 38. Bauhaus; Series 2. Project Files, Subseries 41. ArQule
    - Silver Lake; Correspondence, 1993-1994 (Box 77, Folder 6)
    - Silver Lake; Meetings and conversations, 1993-1994 (Box 77, Folder 7)
    - Silver Lake; Planning and notes, 1993-1994 (Box 77, Folder 8)
    - Silver Lake; Project Players, 1993 (Box 77, Folder 9)
    - Silver Lake; Research, 1994, undated (Box 77, Folder 10)
  - Subseries 43. Mississippi, 1993
    This subseries consists of contact information, correspondence, planning, notes, and research for a project to reclaim the Mississippi-Missouri Rivers at their confluence. The subseries is arranged chronologically.
    - Mississippi River, 1993-1994 (Box 77, Folder 11)
  - Subseries 44. Südraum Leipzig, 1993-1996
    This subseries consists of catalogs, conference information, contact information, contracts and agreements, correspondence, project descriptions, designs and pre-designs, maps, photographic material, planning, notes, proposals, research, and text. As part of the “Art and Landscape” project series, the Harrisons were invited by the Cultural Foundation of the Free State of Saxony and the Cultural Program of the Siemens Corporation to visit the “black” triangle (the borders of Poland, the Czech Republic, and Germany) to study the brown coal open pit mines and respond, as artists, to these landscapes ruined by industrial development processes. The Harrisons did their work at the Okologische station in Borna, Germany, and created a reclamation plan for Tagebau Witznitz. The full name of this project is “The Shape of Turned Earth: A Brown Coal Park for Südraum Leipzig.” The subseries is arranged alphabetically.
    - Südraum Leipzig; Art and Landscape project series, A Brown Coal Park for Südraum Leipzig (Ein Braunkohlepark für den Südraum Leipzig) catalog, 1996 (Box 77, Folder 12)
    - Südraum Leipzig; Art and Landscape project series, Concept, 1993-1994 (Box 77, Folder 13)
    - Südraum Leipzig; Art and Landscape project series, Conferences, 1994-1996 (Box 77, Folder 14)
    - Südraum Leipzig; Contact information, 1994, undated (Box 77, Folder 15)
    - Südraum Leipzig; Contracts and agreements, 1995-1996 (Box 77, Folder 16)
    - Südraum Leipzig; Correspondence, 1993-1994 (Box 77, Folder 17)
    - Südraum Leipzig; Correspondence, 1995-1996 (Box 78, Folder 1)
    - Südraum Leipzig; Descriptions, undated (Box 78, Folder 2)
    - Südraum Leipzig; Designs, 1994, undated (Box 78, Folder 3)
    - Südraum Leipzig; Designs, undated (Map-folder 438)
    - Südraum Leipzig; Designs, undated (Flat-box 270, Folder 5)
    - Südraum Leipzig; Map of Leipzig, Germany, 1993-1994 (Map-tube MT #31)
      See MT #32
      Made up of many smaller maps taped together. Includes a tracing paper overlay. See MT #32
    - Südraum Leipzig; Map of Leipzig, Germany, Tracing paper overlay, 1993-1994 (Map-tube MT #32)
      See MT #31
    - Südraum Leipzig; Maps, 1994, undated (Box 78, Folder 4)
    - Südraum Leipzig; Maps, undated (Flat-box 270, Folder 6)
    - Südraum Leipzig; Photographic material, Negatives, undated (Box 78, Folder 5)
    - Südraum Leipzig; Photographic material, Panorama, undated (Box 78, Folder 6)
    - Südraum Leipzig; Photographic material, Panorama, undated (Flat-box 275, Folder 5)
    - Südraum Leipzig; Photographic material, Photographs, undated (Box 78, Folder 7)
    - Südraum Leipzig; Photographic material, Photographs, undated (Box 78, Folder 8)
    - Südraum Leipzig; Photographic material, Photographs (Copies), undated (Flat-box 279, Folder 4)
    - Südraum Leipzig; Photographic material, Slides, undated (Box 78, Folder 9)
    - Südraum Leipzig; Planning and notes, 1995, undated (Box 78, Folder 10)
    - Südraum Leipzig; Proposals, 1995-1996 (Box 79, Folder 1)
    - Südraum Leipzig; Research and pre-design, 1994, undated (Box 79, Folder 2)
    - Südraum Leipzig; Slide list, undated (Box 79, Folder 3)
    - Südraum Leipzig; Text, 1995-1996 (Box 79, Folder 4)
  - Subseries 45. Green Heart Vision, 1993-1995, 1999-2000
    This subseries consists of catalogs, contact information, contracts and agreements, correspondence, project descriptions, designs, exhibition information, financial records, lectures, presentations, maps, meeting information, photographic material, planning, notes, press, proposals, research, schedules, and text. The Harrisons were invited by the Cultural Council of South Holland to consider the Green Heart of Holland, an area of lowland Holland slowly being reclaimed by the sea. It is a region of dikes, canals, farms, fields, and small villages surrounded by a ring of cities: Amsterdam, Rotterdam, and Utrecht that form the Randstad (Rim City): Amsterdam, Rotterdam, and Utrecht. At the time of this project, the Green Heart was facing expanding urban areas, as well as internal development. Both of which threatened its existence. The Harrisons, using a series of images (ceramic tiles, maps, drawings, and videos) and discourse proposed a new vision for the Green Heart and the Randstad. The full name of this project is “A Vision for the Green Heart of Holland.” The subseries is arranged alphabetically.
    - Green Heart Vision; Contact information, 1995 (Box 79, Folder 5)
    - Green Heart Vision; Contracts and agreements, 1994-1995 (Box 79, Folder 6)
    - Green Heart Vision; Correspondence, 1993-1994 (Box 79, Folder 7)
    - Green Heart Vision; Correspondence, 1995 (Box 79, Folder 8)